Lynn M. Jamieson papers, 1958-2019 C741
Indiana University Archives
Lynn M Jamieson papers
1958-2019
1990-2010
Indiana University Archives
Jamieson, Lynn Marie, 1946-
C741
7 cubic feet 6 rc, 2 dc, 1 small dc
Lynn M. Jamieson was an active faculty member at Indiana University, Bloomington from 1983 to 2018. Jamieson joined the Indiana University Department of Recreation and Park Administration as an Associate Professor, then was promoted to full professorship in 2001 and later became chair of the renamed Department of Recreation, Park and Tourism, among other administrative responsibilities. This collection represents research materials collected by Jamieson as well as her professional activity at IU.
Biographical / Historical
Lynn M. Jamieson (1946-) was born in Paterson, New Jersey. She spent her career working to promote and improve the work of park, recreation, and leisure. Jamieson particularly focused on youth and underserved population, as well as people with disabilities. The importance of this was personal to her, as she contracted polio at age 4 and had an active life as part of her rehabilitation. She had a significant family background in the field of sports and recreation. One of her grandfathers was a high school teacher. Her other grandfather, Walter Jamieson, was a park commissioner in Patterson and worked with his brother and Jamieson's great uncle, Charlie Jamieson, who played professional baseball, to establish a youth league baseball program. Jamieson earned her bachelor's degree in health and physical Education from Muskingum University in the class of 1968. She then began her involvement with Indiana University, earning a master's degree in Physical Education in 1970.
In the years following her first master's degree, Jamieson worked a number of administrative roles in Parks and Recreations departments, in Corpus Christi, Texas; San Diego, California; and Johnson County, Kansas. During this time, she studied part time to earn a second master's degree in Recreation from Indiana University in 1976. She then went on to earn a Doctorated in Recreation from Indiana University in 1980, with a major in Recreation Administration and a minor in higher Education. Her doctoral dissertation was entitled "A Competency Analysis of Recreational Sports in Selected Institutional Settings." During her doctorate, Jamieson was an Associate Instructor in the Department of Recreation and Park Administration as well as working as an intern in the Indiana University Division of Recreational Sports.
Following her Re.D., Jamieson became a full-time member of the faculty of the Recreation Administration department at California Polytechnic State University, from 1980-1993. She primarily taught courses on commercial recreation and recreation administration. In 1985, she also became the Curriculum Coordinator of the Recreation Administration Program. Additionally, in 1986 Jamieson and her husband Stephen Wolter founded the consulting firm Leisure Visions, the name of which was changed to Visions in 1995.
Jamieson joined the Indiana University Department of Recreation and Park Administration in 1993 as an Associate Professor. She taught undergraduate and graduate courses in research, sport management and administration. From 1994 until 1999, Jamieson served as the Assistant Chair for Academic Affairs within the department. In 2001 she was promoted to full professorship at Indiana University and became the Chair of the Department of Recreation, Park, and Tourism, serving as the first female chair in the history of the department. In her role as the chair, she also served as the Executive Director of the Bradford Woods, Hilltop Garden and Nature Center, as well as the National Center on Accessibility. She also oversaw the Eppley Institute for Parks and Public Lands. Her efforts within the department saw changes such as changing the name to Department of Recreation, Park and Toursim and nearly doubling the number of undergraduate students majoring in the department through marketing efforts. In 2008, Jamieson stepped down from her position as Chair but remained as a full Professor within the department. She served as the chair once again from 2015-2017, and retired with the title Professor Emeritus in 2018.
In addition to teaching, Jamieson conducted research on sport and violence, recreational sport competencies,, recreation management, and international sport and leisure policy. The certification program of the National Intermural-Recreational Sports Association was based on her research on competencies in recreational sports. As part of her lengthy research on sport policy, she was a visiting scholar in China, Australia, England, Scotland, Costa Rica, Hong Kong, Turkey, Macau, South Africa, Taiwan, Tanzania, and Zanzibar as part of this research. She was a visiting faculty member at Beijing University of Physical Education in 1997 as well as at the University of Costa Rica in 2003.
Throughout her career, Jamieson was a member of a wide variety of professional organizations, published and presented prolifically, and was very involved in the Indiana University and Bloomington, IN communities. She contributed significantly to her field, and in 2020 was named a Legend within the American Academy for Park and Recreation Administration, which she became a member of in 2005.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Accession 2017/145, transferred by Lynn M, Jamieson December 2017
Related Materials
Additional publications and research materials may be accessed in IUScholarworks
Related photographs may be available in the University Archives Photographs Database
Conditions Governing Access
Select files closed to researchers. Advance notice required for access to collection.
Scope and Contents
The Lynn M. Jamieson papers documents the research and activities of Lynn Jamieson, who was a member of the Indiana University Department of Recreation, Park, and Tourism Studies (now the Department of Heath and Wellness Design) from 1993 until 2018. It contains two series: International Research and Professional Activity.
The International Research series represents Jamieson's research on Sport for All policies, and contains materials spanning 1977 to 2019, with the bulk of the material from 1995 to 2005. It is organized alphabetically into sub-series of ruling bodies, followed by an Individual Files sub-series. Where applicable, sub-series contain front materials files (case documentation, field notes, and transcripts) based upon Jamieson's original file organization and are arranged alphabetically following those files. This series contains materials accumulated by Jamieson in her research on international sport and leisure policy and consists of promotional material (such as pamphlets, booklets, and posters), policy documentation, research on or originating in the area, and transcripts of Jamieson's research interviews.
The Professional Activity series contains materials from 1958 to 2013. It is organized alphabetically, with other level groupings where appropriate. This series contains administrative files on her research, intermixed materials from her education and her teaching career.
Arrangement
The Lynn M. Jamieson papers, 1958-2019, is arranged in two series: International Research 1977-2019 and Professional Activity 1958-2013. The International Research series is divided into subseries based upon ruling body, arranged alphabetically: Australia, 1985-2010; Canada, 1985-2016; China, Hong Kong, 1990-2014; China, Mainland, 1995-2015, Costa Rica, 1990-2003; England, 1999-2010; Kyrgyzstan, 2005-2006; Palau, 2003-2008; Singapore, 1996-2012; South Africa, 1995-2006; Turkey, 1999-2009; United States of America, 1964-2018, and Individual Files 1984-2019. The Individual Files subseries contains ruling bodies with only single files. Files within each subseries are arranged alphabetically by title, with preceding front matter files. The Professional Activity series is arranged alphabetically by title.
Appraisal
Duplicates removed
Custodial History
Gift of Lynn Jamieson, 2017-2022
- International Research, 1977-2019 and undated; 1995-2005 (Box 1)
  - Australia, 1985-2010 and undated; 1995-2005 (Box 1)
    - Case documentation, 1999-2003 (Box 1)
    - Field notes, undated (Box 1)
    - Transcripts, undated; 2 Folders (Box 1)
    - Context, undated (Box 1)
    - Active Australia Presenter Kit, background and exercises, undated (Box 1)
      Arrangement
      The Active Australia Presenter Kit was orginally a binder with tabs, the tab labels have been retained as the folder titles
    - Active Australia Presenter Kit, overhead masters, undated (Box 1)
    - Active Australia Presenter Kit, presentations, undated (Box 1)
    - Active Australia Presenter Kit, presentation floppy disks, undated; 4 Computer Discs; 3.5in Floppy discs (Box 7)
    - Active Australia Presenter Kit, VHS, undated; VHS (Box 7)
    - Active Australia, resource folders, 1999-2000 (Box 1)
    - City plans, 1999-2010 (Box 1)
    - Conference materials, 1998-2002 (Box 1)
    - Leisure, 1998-2002 (Box 1)
    - Magazines, 1996-2004; 3 Folders (Box 1)
    - Melbourne park materials, 1998-2000 (Box 1)
    - Misc. sport publications, 1999-2002 (Box 1)
      General
      Includes materials on parasports and publications from Indigenous Sport Program
    - Policy documentation, 1994-2002; 2 Folders (Box 1)
      Includes materials on women and girls in sports
    - Promotional materials, Active Australia, undated (Box 1)
    - Promotional materials, general, undated; 2 Folders (Box 1)
      Containes materials on parasports and indigienous involvement in sports
    - Recreation industry, 1994-2002 (Box 1)
    - Reports and studies, 1986-1992 (Box 1)
    - Reports and studies, 1993-1998 (Box 1)
    - Reports and studies, 1998-2000 (Box 1)
    - Resource folders, general, 1999-2001 (Box 2)
    - Resources folders, ERA, 1985-2000 (Box 2)
    - Sport education, general, 1991-2001 (Box 2)
    - Sport education, SEPEP, 1994-1995 (Box 2)
  - Canada, 1985-2016 and undated; 2000-2005 (Box 2)
    - Case documentation, 2007 (Box 2)
    - Field notes, 2007 (Box 2)
    - Transcripts, undated (Box 2)
    - Context, undated (Box 2)
    - Athlete development, undated (Box 2)
      Includes materials on disability sports
    - Leisure, 2005-2008 (Box 2)
    - Policy documents, general print-outs, 1985-2007 (Box 2)
      Includes materials on women in sports
    - Policy documents, national, 2002-23012 (Box 2)
    - Policy documents, Ontario, 2006-2010 (Box 2)
    - Research recordings, undated; 3 Audiocassette; Mini-Cassettes (Box 7)
    - Reports/studies, 1985-2016 (Box 2)
  - China, Hong Kong, 1990-2014 and undated (Box 2)
    - Case documentation, 2000-2014 (Box 2)
    - Field notes, undated (Box 2)
    - Transcripts, undated (Box 2)
    - Academic journals, 1997-1999 (Box 2)
    - Leisure, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Policy documents, 1990-2000; 2 Folders (Box 2)
    - Poster, 2010 (Box 2)
    - Reports, 1991-2000; 2 Folders (Box 2)
    - Sport education/coaching, undated (Box 2)
    - Sports context, 1999-2003; 2 Folders (Box 2)
    - Student Stress Management Platform, 2002; Optical disk and sleeve (Box 7)
    - Hong Kong Coliseum Queen Elizabeth Stadium, undated; Optical disk and case (Box 7)
  - China, Mainland, 1995-2015 and undated (Box 3)
    - Case documentation, 1997-2015 (Box 3)
    - Field notes, 1997-2012 (Box 3)
    - Transcripts, 2006 (Box 3)
    - Context, 1995-2015 (Box 3)
    - China Daily, June 6-7, 1997 (Box 3)
    - Leisure, 2006-2014 (Box 3)
    - Oversized items, undated (Box OS 16)
    - Publications, 1997 (Box 3)
    - Restricted materials, 1997 (Box 9)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Restricted
    - SFA binder, intro and annex A-E, undated (Box 3)
    - SFA binder, annex F-H, undated (Box 3)
    - Sport policy, undated (Box 3)
      Includes materials on parasports and ethnic minority groups in sports
    - Teaching, 1997-2009 (Box 3)
    - World Leisure Expo, 2006; 2 Computer Discs; Optical disks and pamphlets (Box 7)
  - Costa Rica, 1990-2003 and undated (Box 3)
    - Case documentation, 2003 (Box 3)
    - Case documentation (restricted), 2003 (Box 9)
    - Field notes, 2003 (Box 3)
    - Transcripts, undated; 3 Folders (Box 3)
    - Leisure, 2000 (Box 3)
    - Literature, 1990-2003; 2 Folders (Box 3)
    - Policy documents, undated; 2 Folders (Box 3)
    - Promotional materials, 1994-2003 (Box 3)
    - Publications, 1990-2002 (Box 3)
    - Semenario Universidad, May 2, 2003 (Box 3)
  - England, 1999-2010 and undated (Box 3)
    - Case documentation, 2000-2008 (Box 3)
    - Transcripts, undated (Box 3)
    - Context, 1999-2009 (Box 3)
    - Periodicals, 1999-2003 (Box 3)
    - Promotional materials, 2001-2002 (Box 3)
    - Sport England cassette, March 11, 2002; Audiocassette (Box 7)
    - Studies and reports, 1999-2010 (Box 3)
  - Kyrgyzstan, 2005-2006 and undated (Box 4)
    - Case documentation, 2005 (Box 4)
    - Transcripts, undated (Box 4)
    - Context, 2006 (Box 4)
    - Calendar, 2005 (Box OS 16)
    - Consent forms (restricted), 2005 (Box 9)
    - Translation CD, 11-1-05; Optical disk (Box 7)
  - Palau, 2003-2008 and undated (Box 4)
    - Customs documentation (restricted), 2008 (Box 8)
    - Leisure, undated (Box 4)
    - Research recording, undated (Box 7)
    - Best of Palau by Kevin Davidson, undated; Optical disk and case (Box 7)
    - The New Shape of Old Island Cultures, 2001 (Box 4)
    - Newspapers, April, 2007 (Box 4)
    - Olympic Committee, undated (Box 4)
    - Youth materials, 2007 (Box 4)
  - Singapore, 1996-2010 and undated (Box 4)
    - Case documentation, 1996-2006 (Box 4)
    - Field notes, undated (Box 4)
    - Transcripts, undated (Box 4)
    - Context, 1996-2010 (Box 4)
    - Promotional materials, 1999-2002 (Box 4)
  - South Africa, 1995-2006 (Box 4)
    - Policy draft, 1995 (Box 4)
    - SISA and Special Olympics, 1996-2006 (Box 4)
  - Turkey, 1999-2009 and undated (Box 4)
    - Case documentation, 2005-2009 (Box 4)
    - Field notes, undated (Box 4)
    - Indiana University, 2005 (Box 4)
    - Leisure, undated (Box 4)
    - Periodicals, 2004-2005 (Box 4)
    - Publications, 1999-2004 (Box 4)
    - Turkey Universiade, 2005 (Box 4)
    - Fitness poster, undated (4a)
  - United States of America, 1964-2018 and undated; 1990-2018 (Box 4)
    - Case documentation, 1999-2009 (Box 4)
    - Context, undated (Box 4)
    - Academic publications on sports, 1980-2007 (Box 4)
    - Books, 1964-2008 (Box 4)
    - Disability, 2005-2011 (Box 4)
    - Indiana, 2007-2011 (Box 4)
    - Newspapers, 1998-2008 (Box 4)
    - 21st Annual North American Society for Sport Management Conference, May 30th -June 3rd, 2006 (Box 7)
    - Parks & Rec, General, 1999-2018; 2 Folders (Box 4)
    - Parks & Rec, Professional development, 1987-2013 (Box 5)
    - Parks & Rec, Promotional materials, 1998-2007 (Box 5)
    - Presidents Challenge Instructional DVD, undated; Optical disk and case (Box 7)
    - Presidents Council, General, 1996-2006 (Box 5)
    - Presidents Council, Resource folders, 1996-2008 (Box 5)
    - Research, Booklets, 1994-2006; 2 Folders (Box 5)
    - Research, Bound materials 1 of 2, 1999-2008; 2 Folders (Box 5)
    - Research, Loose materials, 1977-2015 (Box 5)
    - Research, Pamphlets, 1996-2007 (Box 5)
    - Research recordings, undated; 9 Audiocassette; Mini-audiocassettes (Box 7)
    - Resource folders, 1992-2007 (Box 5)
    - Sport for All DC, undated; Optical disk (Box 7)
  - Individual Files, 1984-2019 and undated (Box 5)
    - Columbia, Circa. 2019 (Box 5)
    - Europe, 1994; 2001 (Box 5)
      Includes materials on the Special Olympics
    - Greece, 1999-2007 (Box 5)
    - Government Policy Background Information CD, undated; Optical disk (Box 7)
    - Hungary, 2000-2005 (Box 5)
    - Hungary (restricted materials), 2003 (Box 9)
    - International, 1984-2004 (Box 5)
    - Ireland, 2010 (Box 5)
    - Japan, 2005 (Box 5)
    - Kenya and Malawi, undated (Box 5)
    - Korea, 2009 (Box 5)
    - Malaysia, undated (Box 5)
    - New Zealand, 1995-2009 (Box 5)
    - Poland, 2010 (Box 5)
    - Scotland, 2005-2010 (Box 5)
    - Sweden, 1990-1993 (Box 5)
    - Taiwan, 2012 (Box 5)
    - Tanzania, 2005-2016 (Box 5)
    - Uraguay, 1994 (Box 5)
    - Zanzibar, 2007-2011 (Box 5)
    - Research recordings (unspecified), undated; 31 Audiocassette; Mini-audiocassettes (Box 8)
- Professional Activity, 1958-2013 and undated (Box 6)
  - Blank consent forms, 2000-2007 (Box 6)
  - Conference materials, 2006 (Box 6)
  - IRB amendments and letters, 1995-2006 (Box 6)
  - MacLean collected materials, 1966-1982 (Box 6)
    - Lectures, 1966-1982 (Box 6)
    - Maria Carter papers, 1969-1975 (Box 6)
  - MacLean Lectures, 1958-1983 (Box 6)
    - Aging, 1979-1981 (Box 6)
    - Leisure, 1963-1983 (Box 6)
    - Other topics, 1958-1973 (Box 6)
  - Monograph and article printouts, 1975-1999 (Box 6)
  - Politics and the Sports World, undated (Box 6)
  - SFA research, Documentation, 1985-2013 (Box 6)
  - SFA research, Surveys, 1996 (Box 6)
  - Signed consent forms & paperwork (restricted), 2000-2001 (Box 9)
  - Signed consent forms & paperwork (restricted), 2002-2007 (Box 9)
  - Syllabus for Introduction to research, 1967 (Box 6)
  - Teaching, 1977-2002 (Box 6)
    - General, undated (Box 6)
    - R539, 2002; 2 Folders (Box 6)
    - R512 & R424, 1980-2002 (Box 6)
    - T590, Notes, 1977-2000; 2 Folders (Box 6)
    - T590, Student work, 1999-2000 (Box 6)
    - Student work (restricted), undated (Box 9)
  - Thesis Outline Guide, 2000 (Box 6)